融资的过程就好似一场摩诃婆罗多之战
Getting a funding is equal to fighting the battle of Mahabharatha
我至少要占股51%
I want atleast 51%
明天还有个活动，不会有潜在的投资者吗？
Tomorrow, you have an event, won't there be potential investors?
我们没时间了，史瑞雅
We are running out of time, Shreya
这么说只有你们三个？
So only 3 of you guys?
不，先生，我们有四个人，杰图正在来的路上
No sir, we are four of us. Jeetu is on his way
喂，尤吉，我不能去了，我爸突然来我家了
Yogi i can't come, All of a sudden dad showed up!
等一下，杰图
Wait a minute Jitu.
回来坐下
Sit over here.
真的非常抱歉，但这是我第四次告诉您
I'm really really sorry sir, but this is the fourth time i'm telling you
除非团队人到齐了，否则我不能给你们通行证
that i can not give you the passes until the entire team registered
所以我们这样，在你们的报价后面……
So the amount which you guys had proposed?
加一个零
Suffix a zero to the number.
我需要一个陪审室
I need a jury room.
兄弟们，不是这样的，每次我在陪审室里做出决定都是正确的
You know, whenever I've taken a decision in the jury room, it's always been right
他他妈的扔了一枚硬币然后就定了
He fucking tosses a coin and decides.
作出决定依据是抛硬币的过程，而不是抛硬币的结果
Decision was taken on the basis of tossing the coin, not on the result of it.
如果只是因为钱，那我不能让任何人控制我的野心
Just for more funding I can't let anyone control my ambitions.
我们要去哪儿？
Where are we going ?
回去继续参加活动
Back to the event.
但是如果他们不让我们进去呢
But what if they don't let us in!
那就用我们的一贯操作
The same thing what we always do ..
试试
Try.
我们做过的最厉害的事情就是没放弃
爸爸，我刚给你煮了咖啡
Dad, I just made you some coffee
我去帮你拿
Let me get it for you
不用，你坐下
No No, Just sit down
杰图刚刚还在这里
Jeetu was just right here
我打了30分钟的瞌睡
I dozed off for 30 minutes
他就不见了
and he is nowhere to be seen
他告诉你他去哪儿了吗？
Did he tell you where he has gone?
没有，但他一定就在附近
No but he must be around the block
他马上就回来
He'll be back in a jiffy
是吗？
Oh yeah?
他通常什么时候从办公室回家？
when does he usually get back home from the office?
大概在晚上7点到7:30
almost by 7PM or 7:30 PM
但是门卫告诉我，他晚上一般两三点钟回来
But watchman told me that he usually gets back by 2 or 3 in the night
有时候他第二天早上才回来
and sometimes he'd get back next day in the morning
是的，有时候
yeah sometimes
但他会提前打电话告诉我他会晚点回家
But he tells me beforehand on the phone if he's gonna be home late
是吗？
oh really?
你能从电话里看出他是在办公室里说话吗？
can you tell from the phone that he's speaking from the office?
他可能是从任何地方打来的
He could be calling from anywhere
什么意思
I don't follow
我从网上查到了他的公司
Look, I took the contact number from the website
给他的公司打了电话
and called his company
他们告诉我那个办公室已经关门两天了
They told me that office has been closed for two days
你知道这两天他去哪儿了吗？
Now do you know where he's been for last 2 days?
我不知道，爸爸
Umm No Dad
桑亚……
Soumya...
你和他……
You and him...
相处得很好，对吗？
are getting along with each other, right?
当然了，爸爸，但是……
Ofcourse Dad but...
但是您要说什么？
But what's the matter?
不，没什么
No It's nothing
问题是他才26岁
Thing is that he's just 26 years old
我们不知道他和谁有联系
we don't know who he's been associating with
你这样
Do one thing..
看好他
Keep an eye on him
监控他的手机，信用卡和账单
Monitor his phones, credit cards and bills
检查他衣服上的唇印，如果有的话
Check for the lipstick marks on his clothes, if any
哦，是的……
oh yes and..
切一些洋葱和香菜叶
Chop some onion and coriander leaves
然后放进蔬菜里。
and put it in the vegetable..
再煮5分钟
and cook for 5 more minutes
杰图的妈妈就是这么做的
Jeetu's mom follows the same recipe
你去哪儿了，孩子？
So Where were you, Son?
哦，我只是在外面慢跑
Oh I was just jogging outside
穿人字拖跑？
In flip flops?
其实我跑得很慢
I.. I was running at a slow pace actually
下次尽量快一点
Try at a fast pace next time
好了，现在把你的手机给我
Alright now give me your phone
我得给你阿姨打个电话
I have to call your Aunt
我给她打吧？
Why don't I call her?
我已经很久没和她说过话了
It's been a long time since I've spoken to her
那好吧
Okay, very well then
那你给她打电话
You call her then
用杰图的手机打给她，然后跟我聊聊她最近怎样
Call her from Jeetu's phone and tell me how's she doing
我在外面看报纸
I'll be out here reading newspaper
我不能再这么做了
I can't do this anymore
为什么? 发生什么了？
Why? What happened?
他以为你外面有人了
He thinks that you're having a love affair with someone
让我监视你
He was asking me to spy on you
这都是因为那个白痴门卫
this is all because of that moronic watchman
我要写一份开除他的请愿书
gotta write a petition for his expulsion
而且纳文和队友们最近发生了很多事
Also Naveen and team has been going through a lot lately
到晚上我们就会知道该怎么走下一步了
We'll know by the evening what we're gonna do with the startup
你真的没有外遇，对吗？
Umm you're really not having an affair. right?
桑亚你怎么……
Soumya What the...
我都已经跟不上工作的节奏了而你却在谈论外遇？
I can't even keep up with my job here and you're taking about affair?
那你为什么不告诉爸爸？
Then why don't you tell this to Dad?
你辞职了，加入了创业公司。
That you've left the job and about this startup..
现在还不是时候
It's not the right time yet
那要等到什么时候？
So, when it's gonna be?
他迟早会知道的
He's gonna know about it one way or another
通过办公室或者门卫，或者从其他地方
Through Office or by watchman or maybe from some other place
你最好自己告诉他
it's better that you tell him about it yourself
伙计们，我不是开玩笑
Guys I'm not joking
我妈妈过去常常亲吻我的额头以求好运
My mom used to kiss me on my forehead for luck
我每次考试都成功了
and it worked every time in my exams
我们的额头上有一个神圣的紫色脉轮
We have a sacred purple chakra in our forehead
我告诉你，我们一直被坏运气束缚着
I'm telling you, we've been girdled by bad luck
有人吻我的额头，一切都会好起来的
Someone kiss me on my forehead, everything will be alright
等等，曼达尔，我们得先找到评委
Hold up Mandal, We gotta find the judges first
你知道我怎么想的吗？
You know what I think?
把其他人都放在一边，让我们把注意力集中在 纳拉扬·默西 (INFOSYS 的创始人)身上
Leave everyone else aside and let's focus on Narayan Murthy(founder of INFOSYS*)
听着，我不在乎进入或许可
Look, I don't care about entry or permission
但是我要让那个婊子阿波娃付出代价！ 纳文！
嘿，阿米特什！
Hey Amitesh!
你怎么样，混蛋？
How're you doing fucker?
我很好，你呢？
I'm well and good. How about you?
你吃午饭了吗？
Did you have the lunch yet?
还没有，兄弟
Not yet bro
伙计，你错过了最好的黄油鸡肉
Man, you're missing out on the best butter chicken out there
我已经吃了6盘了
I've already eaten 6 plates
现在快去排队吧，他们只剩这么多了
Get in the line now, they only have so much left
但你他妈的在这里干什么？
But what the fuck are you doing here?
你也创建了一个创业公司吗？
Did you create a startup too?
你能帮我拿一下吗？
Can you hold this for me?
小心糕点
Watch out for the pastry
什么，你说什么？
What? what did you say?
每个星期天都有一个活动或者峰会
Every Sunday there's an Event or E summit
我注册只是为了来这吃鸡肉
And I just register only to gulp a lot of chicken
看，我甚至给了他们一个提示
Look, I even give them a hint
Petpooja.com (* Hungerlust.com)
petpooja.com (*Hungerlust.com)
但是一直没有人知道我的诡计
But still no one has come to know about my shenanigans
那你呢？
What about you though?
你们的创业理念是什么？
What's the idea of your startup?
我们可能会在台上展示我们的想法
we're presenting our idea on the stage most likely
到时你就知道了
Then you'll know
还等什么? 现在就告诉我
Why so closemouthed about it? Tell me now
好吧，我们的想法是..。
Okay, so the idea is...
如果我现在告诉你，不会降低你的期望值吗？
Won't it lower your anticipation if I told you now?
大学毕业后你一点都没变
you haven't changed a bit since college
没有人比你更戏剧化了
No one could be more melodramatic than you
好吧，就让它成为一个谜吧
alright let it be a mystery then
杰图在哪儿？
Where the hell is Jeetu?
那个混蛋在家里，就是因为他，我们才落得如此地步
The fucker's at home, it's because of him that we're in such abyss
是吗？
oh really?
是啊
yeah
我们现在得和评委谈谈
We have to talk to the judges now
纳拉扬·穆西来了吗？
Is Narayan Murthy here yet?
他在最后一刻退出了这场活动
He abandoned the event at the last moment
因此，活动工作人员现在已经找到了一个新的替代者
So the event staff has seeked a new replacement now
我听说他是一个资深的、经验丰富的人
I've heard that he's a doyen and very experienced man
我刚才在这附近看到他了
I just saw him around here somewhere
是的，就是他
Yeah, that's him
穿着黑色西装
In the black suit
我想不起他的名字了。
I can't recollect his name..
哦，是的，拉杰 · 卡纳
Oh yes Rajat Khanna
莫卡特孟买分部负责人
Head of Mokart's Mumbai branch
你是要去亲他吗？？？
Do you want the kiss here or in the bathroom?
已经两个小时了，还是锁着的
It's been 2 hours but no one's bothering to unlock this thing
今年的女性参会人数都破纪录了
women have a record participation this year
5位女企业家，竟然这样
5 Female entrepreneurs and this?
我跟你讲，性别歧视也要有个限度
I tell you there has to be a limit to gender discrimination
我是说它无处不在
I mean it's everywhere
在商界，体育界，电影界
In business, in sports, in films
你知道贝克德尔测试吗？
Do you know about the Bechdel test?
不知道
No
来吧，我告诉你来
Come, I'll tell you come
他认识你，试着和他谈谈
He knows you, try talking to him
老哥，我为了办这家公司打乱了他的计划
Dude, I stomped over his project to start this startup
不可能的
There's no chance
收到
Roger that
两分钟后见
See you in two
一切都准备好了
Everything is set
15分钟后我们就能拿到通行证了
We'll be holding the passes in our hands in next 15 minutes
什么，怎么做到的？
What? how?
我只是花了一些时间在人类最具创造力的椅子上
I just spent some time on mankind's most creative chair
我充分利用了它
And I made good use of it
我有3个惊人的计划来参加这个比赛
I have 3 amazing plans to enter this competition
尤吉，别搞那些花里胡哨的
Yogi no violence, no kidnapping
我有一个参加比赛的绝妙计划
I have 1 amazing plan to enter the competition
听我说，这是万无一失的
Hear me out, It's foolproof
计划是这样的
Here's the plan
你们以为自己了解所有的总体规划，对吗？
You guys think that you've heard all the masterplans before, right?
但你们不知道我的
But not mine
有些计划是有效的，有些计划是机智的
Some plans are effective, some plans are brilliant
我的两者都是
Mine is both
5分钟后，阿波娃会在接待处接到一个电话
Right after 5 minutes, Apoorva will recieve a call on the reception
她会到外面去接电话
In order to attend it, she'll go outside
此时曼达尔用气球挡住监控摄像头
Mandal will then block the CCTV by balloons
然后我来转移注意力
And then my diversion
什么? 是真的吗？
What? Is that true?
伙计们，有人看到萨钦在外面
Guys, Sachin was just spotted outside
不是萨钦·德鲁卡，是萨钦·班萨（印度富豪）
Not Sachin Tendulkar you morons, Sachin Bansal
最后纳文要做的是
Finally, all Naveen has to do
把杰图的头像换成别人的
is replace Jeetu's face on our company's profile with somebody else's
就是我们今天的假杰图
And that guy will be our fake Jeetu for a day
等下
NO no no no
你要上传谁的照片来取代杰图？
Whose photo are you gonna upload in place of Jeetu's?
我们需要一个假的杰图
We need a fake Jeetu beforehand
计划很简单，纳文
Plan is foolproof Naveen
我们我们已经有第四个人了
We have the 4th guy
我刚雇佣了我们的第一个实习生
I've just hired our first intern
他来了
Oh! and he's here
钥匙在脚垫下面
The key is under the doormat
老子能活一百
Live Long Suckers
让我们为恰恰鼓掌
Let's give it up for ChaCha
尤吉，我不太确定，兄弟
Yogi, I'm not so sure bro
你有更好的计划吗？
Do you have a better plan?
那么来吧，我们开始吧
Then come on guys lets do this
你为什么把气球拿进去？
Why are you taking the balloons inside?
今天是我儿子的生日
It.. it's my son's birthday
你儿子是谁？
who is your son?
纳文
Naveen
这里没有纳文
There's no Naveen here
你这气球里面藏了什么？
What are you smuggling inside them?
我要报警了
I'm calling the police
我不想再被关进监狱了
I don't want to get locked behind the bars again
负责人，报警
Organizer, call the ploice
等等，等等
Whoa hold on hold on
他跟我一起的，发生什么事了？
He's with me what happened?
他为什么把气球带到这里来？
Why is he bringing the balloons in here?
你们又来了？
You guys again?
保安，请他们出去，他们已经烦了我好几个小时了
Security, please escort them out of here They have been bugging me for hours
这是怎么回事？
What's going on here?
怎... 怎么了？
Wha.. what's the problem?
纳文？
Naveen?
你们应该早点来找我的
You guys have been here since morning You should've come to me earlier
刚才那是在搞什么？
What the hell was that out there?
先生，通行证准备好了
Sir, the passes sir
我真的很抱歉，我不知道你认识他们
I'm really sorry I didn' know that you know them
就算我不认识他们
Even if I didn't know them
你怎么能阻止别人参加比赛？
How dare you stop people from entering the competition?
非常抱歉，先生
i'm really sorry sir
他们不是已经在网站上注册了吗？
Haven't they already registered on the website?
他们还没有准备好产品吗？
Don't they have a product ready?
是的，先生，我真的很抱歉
They do sir, i'm really sorry
所以我觉得你应该和管理层谈谈让她滚蛋
So I think you should talk to the management and get her fired
是的，就该这样，不是吗？
Yeah we should. shouldn't we?
这样就不会有别的队伍因为一个微不足道的规则而被取消比赛资格
So that more teams don't get disqualified for a trivial rule
没关系，先生，她只是在做她的工作
It's okay sir, she was just doing her job
非常感谢您
thank you so much sir
如果我们能报答你的恩惠
If we can ever return your favour
实际上我叔叔是 LIC 的代理人
Actually my uncle is an LIC agent
如果你需要免费保险，这是我的名片
If you ever need a free insurance policy, here's my card
不用了，谢谢你
it's ok
你们工作这么努力，这是我能为我的前雇员做的最起码的事
You guys have worked so hard, this is the least I could do for My ex employee
非常感谢，能遇到你真的很幸运
Thanks a lot, lucky for us that you were here
这点我同意
That I would agree with
只有一件小事
Just one small thing
有些人可能会误会，因为我在开始前就跟你们见面了
Some people might feel that because I know you from before I'm allowing you to participate
然而这里禁止发生有争议的事情，会影响我的形象
So, god forbids if there's a controversy to follow, making me a bad person
你们能不能让其他团队签一份说明让他们同意你参赛
Can you just get the other teams to sign on a paper That they're okay with you participating
其他团队? ，所有其他团队吗？
Others as in? all the other teams?
对的，应该不会超过半小时
yeah, it shouldn't take more than half an hour
而且他们现在肯定在吃午饭
Plus they must be having lunch right now
我不想让其他队伍觉得评委有偏见，懂我的意思吧？
See, I don't want the other teams to feel that the judges are biased, right?
所以，为了安全起见，去找大家签名吧
So, just for safety please get the signatures
好吗，其他评委在等，我我得走了
Okay? okay the other judges are waiting for me I gotta go
但是拉杰，如果我们拿不到签名怎么办？
But Rajat, what if we don't get the signatures?
没有其他团队的同意，我不能让你上台演讲，纳文
Without the other teams' consent I can't allow you to talk about your product Naveen
纳文，你知道我的风格
Naveen you know me
无论规则多么琐碎，但我还是愿意遵守
However trivial the rules are you know I always like to follow them
活动就要开始了
The event's gonna start
请拿到签名
Please get the signatures
是的，我今晚就到
Yes I'm getting there tonight
不，我还没走
No I haven't left yet
我会在晚上8点出发
I'll leave by 8PM
不是啊，为什么我明天早上才到？
No, why would I reach the next morning?
不会的，我今晚就到
I won't be late, I'll be there tonight
我不坐火车了
I won't be taking train
杰图给我订了一张机票
Jeetu booked me a flight ticket
是的，他最近升职了
Yes, he just got a promotion
好吧，我晚点再跟你说
Alright man, I'll talk to you later
怎么了？
What happened?
没什么，我只是想看会电视
Nothing, I'm just going to watch TV
这应该有个遥控器
There was a remote around here
你看到了吗？
Do you see it there?
你要看什么？
What are you gonna watch?
三傻就要开始了
3 Idiots is about to start
你看过了吗？
Have you seen it?
是的，重播很多次了
Yeah, it's been broadcasted a lot
不过我还没看完整部电影
I haven't seen the whole movie though
什么，你还没看完整部电影吗？
What? you haven't seen the whole movie?
这是一部很棒的电影
It's a brilliant movie
高潮部分很棒，在迈德哈万和他爸爸之间有一个场景
The climax is awesome, There's a scene between Madhavan and his Dad
来，我给你看看现在是不是在播
Here, I'll show you if it's airing right now
你看过“丈夫，妻子和她”吗？
Have you seen "Husband, wife and her" ?
桑吉夫 · 库马尔的电影
Sanjeev Kumar's film
没有
Nope
这也是一部很棒的电影
It's a brilliant movie too
在影片中，桑吉夫 · 库马尔与其他女人有染
In the film sanjeev kumar has an affair with other woman
毁了他的生活
which sabotaged his life
你看过吗？
Have you seen it?
不，我没有
No I haven't
一定在经典频道播出，去看看
It must be airing on a classic channel, check it
没有，他们正在播放的是巴格班
Nope, They are showing Baghban here
现在只有广告
Right now it's just commercials
你为什么要看广告，换频道
Why are you watching the commercials, Change the channel
不，我只是注意到广告市场已经完全改变了
No, I'm just noticing that Ad world is completely changed now
它不再只是洗发水和发油的广告了
Its not only shampoo and hair oil ads anymore
现在有很多关于网站域名和智能手机应用程序的广告
There are a lot of commercials about website domains and smartphone apps these days
是的
Yeah
现在所有的事情都在互联网上完成
Everything's been done on Internet these days
甚至这些电影演员也做了很多与科技相关的广告
Even these movie actors are doing a lot of tech related ads
这些应用程序非常有用
These apps are very useful though
我早上就是通过一个应用程序预订了你的航班
I even booked your flight through an app in the morning
这些开发应用程序的公司最初被称为创业公司
These app generating companies are initially termed as "Startup"
在过去的7、8年里，人们已经变得更加精通技术
People have been more tech savvy since the last 7,8 years
那又怎样？
So what?
关于创业公司你想告诉我什么? 你以为我不知道吗？
What are you telling me about Startup? Don't I know about it?
不，电视上播放着一则广告，我就这么说一嘴……
No, there was an ad playing on the TV that's why..
你怕不是在创业公司工作吧？
Do you have a job offer from a startup?
那就是你下班后去的地方吗？
That's where you work post the office hours?
听着，不要轻信这些
Look, don't be gullible about it
大多数创业公司只是诱饵
Most startups are just decoys
他们不会给你钱，相反，他们会给你股份
They won't offer you any money, Instead they'll give you a share
如果公司在短短6个月内倒闭，你将如何处理这些股份？
What'll you do with the share if company shuts down in mere 6 months?
爸爸，事情不是这样的
That's not how it works Dad
事情就是这样的，你不用告诉我
That's exactly how it works. You don't have to tell me about it
萨蒂什的儿子也开了一家雨伞厂，但什么也没有得到。
Satish's son opened an umbrella factory too, nothing has come out of it.
我们不做雨伞
We're not making umbrellas
不管你做啥
Yeah whatever you're making
你能保证公司不会在6个月后倒闭吗？
Can you give me a guarantee that the company is not gonna terminate after 6 months?
不能去创业公司工作，明白吗？
Don't even think about working in a startup, okay?
你听到了吗？
Do you hear me?
是的
Yeah
你妈妈给了我一个歌曲下载列表，去下载吧
Your mom gave a list of songs to download, Get to that
现在就去
Go now
爸爸！
Dad!
事实上，他没有跟你说实情
Actually, he didn't tell you the whole thing
先生，你已经吃了7盘了
Sir, you've already eaten 7 plates
你在给我计数吗？
You're counting down this? huh?
我是创业者，你怎么敢这么说？
I'm a startup founder, how dare you?
这又不是你儿子的婚礼，快点，快点
It's not your son's wedding, keep 'em coming. chop chop
嘿 阿米特，兄弟，能帮个忙吗
Hey Amitesh bro, there's a problem
真扫兴
Oh! that's a bummer
还有其他人签名了吗？
Has anyone else signatured yet?
没有，但是每个人都在问同样的问题
No, but everyone's asking the same thing
这就是我来找你的原因
That's why I came to you
请您签个名好吗？
Can I have your signature please?
等我吃完这道甜菜，我就签字
Just let me finish this sweet dish then I'll sign on it
我两分钟后回来
I'll be back in 2 minutes
等一下
Just a minute
在找钢笔吗？
Looking for a pen?
不，我的电话在响，等一下
No, my phone is buzzing. Hold on
是卡鲁尼什，不好意思
Karunesh
是的，卡鲁尼什，是的，你说，是的
Yeah Karunesh, yeah speak up. Yeah
你面条吃没了？
You ran out of noodles?
你们能在这里签字吗？
Can you guys just sign here?
滚开，混蛋。
Beat it, asshole.
我告诉你，邪恶的眼神非常有用
I'm telling you evil eye beads are very useful
以前有个男孩经常骚扰我的表妹，我就是这样吓跑他的
Some boy used to harass my cousin sister and it helped
她是一个非常真诚的女孩，兄弟，她挂你电话是因为你说了很多脏话
She's a very sincere girl bro, your phone hangs because you use lot of profanity
滚出去
Get out of here
但你们不是……
But you guys are..
关心他人
滚
Beat it, fucker
什么，你做了煎蛋卷？
What? you made an Omelet?
天啊! 那些鸡蛋是我用来洗头的
Oh man! I brought those eggs to wash my hair with
你这个混蛋！
You jerk!
阿米特，签名吧，兄弟
Amitesh, Please sign it bro
天啊，我又要拉屎了
Oh man! I've to take a shit again
我想我拉肚子了，我马上回来，好吗？
I think I've diarrhea I'll be right back, okay?
是的，你说得对，今天就聊到这吧
Yeah you're right It's enough talking for the day
那啥，你想听首歌吗？
Listen, you wanna hear a song?
当然了，请记住
of course，please keep in mind
所有团队的介绍时间必须控制在五分钟之内
all team will has to end presentations in 5 mins
在正式评选开始之前……
now, before we start the main event of this years xxx
请把你们的掌声
please. give a big applause
给到今晚的嘉宾，拉杰·康纳
for the xxx of the day, mr.Rajat Khanna
其实当他们找我当评委的时候
you know, when this guys approachies me to be the judge for this event
the first question i ask was……
我首先想到的就是……
为什么要找我呢
why me？
请他们俩来我能理解，但是……
i mean i can understand why xxx and xxx, but……
我可不像他……
i'm not the CEO of...what
公司市值多少？4亿？
400 million dollar
再多一点
Just a little bit more
4亿市值公司的CEO
400 million dollar company like xxx
我也不是年轻有活力的运输业巨头公司高管
and i'm not the young and dynamic xxx transportion giant like uber
我们还是个初创公司
we still start up
而且我很抱歉我也不是吴彦祖
and i'm sorry i'm not xxx
但是他们说我是组织中重要的成员
so they said "no no, you've been a member of the xxx team"
我有责任为国家的发展做出贡献
so you're responsible for the expansion in all 50 countrys
我说是的，我是团队成员没错，但至于是不是重要成员
i said yes was certainly the member of the team, but xxx
只有我的董事长能告诉你
only my board director can tell you
我今天来这里
you know, the real reason
真正的原因是在座的各位
i want to be here, and i'm here today, it's you guys
看看这个会场
i mean look at this, this is amazing
满满的都是创业人才
it makes my heart full of joy to see a room full of young xxx
大家正在掀起一场革命，可能你们都没有意识到
you know you guys are creating a revolution and you don't even know it
记住我的话
Mark my words
the face of this nation is going to be change
这个国家的面貌将会改变
不会因为政客而改变，也不会因为明星
not by politicians or stars
而是因为在座的各位
it's going to be change by you guys
没关系，至少我们试过了
It's alright man, atleast we tried
别这么消沉
Don't fret over it
我们要回去吗？
Should we go home?
如果我们现在出发，还能避开交通拥堵
We'll beat the traffic jam if we leave now
叫他闭嘴，尤吉
Tell him to zip it, Yogi
但是纳文这一次我同意他的观点
But Naveen for once I agree with him bro
我们已经受了够多苦
We've had enough of this shit
我们现在不应该在讲台上出丑
We shouldn't embarass ourselves on the stage now
回家吧
Let's go home now
不，尤吉
No Yogi
我们不能就这样放弃
We're not gonna leave it like this
我们为这个评审奋斗了这么久
We've been fighting for this competition for so long
我们再也不会在同一个屋檐下见到这么多金主了
We won't meet so many investors under one roof anytime again
我们必须上台
We have to get on the stage
但是我们在台上应该做什么呢？
But what shall we do on the stage?
你在这家创业公司的工作是什么？
What's your job in this startup?
编程
Coding
如果你要编程，那为什么要离开一个稳定的公司呢？
If you had to do coding then what's the point of leaving a well settled company?
爸爸，我不知道该怎么解释
Dad, I don't know how to explain
不，不，试着解释
No No try to explain
但你在解释的时候，请看着我的眼睛
But look into my eyes while explaining
爸爸，我的工作没有满足感
Dad, there's no job satisfaction
我不喜欢那些稳定的公司
I don't enjoy working in these companies
享受？
Enjoy?
工作是让你享受的吗？
Do you seek enjoyment by working?
我在银行工作了32年，是为了享受吗？
I've been working in a bank for 32 years, what? for enjoyment?
我必须管理别人的账户，为了什么? 为了享受？
I have to manage other people's accounts, what? for enjoyment?
你在每个月的第一天就能领工资
You get the salary on the 1st day of every month
这么好的工作，你有社保和公积金
You had such a good job, you had PFLT and all the company's amenities
即使这样你还是选择了出来创业？
Even after all that you decided to choose this?
好吧，忘记你犯的错误，继续前进
Alright forget the mistake that you've done and move on
你的简历很出色
You have a promising resume
重新申请一份新工作，一两个月后你就又上班了，好吗？
Start applying for a new job, you'll get one in a month or two, okay?
爸爸我已经..。
Dad, I've already...
好吗？
Okay?
不好，爸爸
Not okay Dad
他想继续创业
He wants to carry on with the startup
你们是一点都没听进去吧？
Aren't you guys getting anything?
如果公司做的不好或者创业失败了怎么办？
What if the company didn't succeed or the startup crashes. What then?
至少给他一次失败的机会，爸爸
Atleast give him a chance to fail, Dad
前面有一颗地雷，你却要我让他踩上去？
There's a landmine ahead, and you're asking me to let him step on that?
你考研的时候，我有个升职的机会在斋浦尔
When you were having your exams, I was offered a promotion in Jaipur
为了你的学业，我拒绝了升职
For the sake of your studies, I denied the promotion
我总是说，你想学多少就学多少
I have always said that study as much as you want
我来还贷款，我不会让你有任何的负担
I'll pay the loans but I won't let all the burden fall on you
为了你好，我不允许你这么做
I'm disallowing this for your own good
但是爸爸，你还要操多少心？
But Dad, for how long are you gonna be concerned?
作为父母，你所能做的就是让他做好准备
As a parent all you can do is prepare him
这样他才能为自己着想
So that he can think about his own good himself
你已经做到了
And you've done that
你可以传授学生知识，但学生必须自己参加考试
You can teach a student but he has to take the exam himself
好吧，看来我的话在这里没有任何意义
Alright then, it seems like my words have no meaning here
爸爸，你曾经还为了他的未来放弃了升职
Dad, even you took a risk of your promotion for his future
现在他为了自己的未来而辞职，至少要对他有信心
Now that he's leaving his job for his own future, atleast have faith in him
我对一家有25年历史的公司有信心
I have faith in a company which is 25 years old
但是你要我我怎么能相信一个由4个业余爱好者创建的创业公司
How can I trust a new company created by 4 amateurs
但是这个有25年历史的公司也是由3到4个业余爱好者创建的
But that 25 years old company was also created by some 3,4 amateurs
这家公司成立的那天，就有99家公司倒闭
And the day that company was created, another 99 companies were shut down
想想这概率，儿子
Probability Jeetu..
1%
1/100
如果你学过概率，那你应该能做出更明智的决定
If you had studied that chapter, your rank and decision both would've been better
爸爸，给他个机会
爸爸，别走
对不起
我没能说服他
嘿，你为什么哭？
Hey! why are you crying?
反正他也不会留下来
He wouldn't have stayed anyway
我不该说的
I shouldn't have said anything
好了，别哭了
Alright now please don't cry
对不起
你知道吗? 从来没有人像你一样为我挺身而出
You know what? No one has ever stood up for me like you did
你已经尽力了，亲爱的
You tried your best dear
你为什么说对不起？
Why are you saying sorry?
我应该谢谢你才对
Infact I should say thanks to you
我们的婚姻是包办的，所以我从来没有对你说过句话
We had an arranged marriage so I've never said this to you
我爱你
I love you
我也爱你
i love you too
抱歉我插一句
sorry for interrupting but...
我不能在你们app上买任何东西？
i can't not order xxx and xxx and anything else in the app?
不能
no, not even xxx
而且我为之骄傲
and i am proud of it
我们"枕头柳"只关注一样商品，那就是……
we here at pillow willow, are focusing only on one thing
枕头
pillows
至少接下来的三个季度是这样的
at least for next 3 Quarters
我们想要像flip cart一样
we want to be like flip card
但是只做枕头
but only for pillows
但是……
but uh...
flip cart 早就有枕头了，对吧？
flip card already has pillows right?
我想你的时间到了，谢谢
i guess that's all you can xxx thank you
谢谢大家
thank you xxx and team everyone
下面有请22号团队
next one we have team no.2
让我们欢迎
please welcome xxx and xxx
纳文团队
from i am in door
接下来的五分钟舞台归你们
guys the stage is yours for next 5 mins
大家好
我是纳文
你一小时前肯定见过我和我的团队成员
I'm sure you must have met me and my team members an hour ago
我们就是刚才到处乞求的人
We're the same guys who were like pleading, begging..
甚至可能还威胁了你
And in some cases even threatning you
只为在这张纸上签个名
To get one lousy signature on this page
可以让我们可以在舞台上讲述产品的说明
Which says it's okay for us to present our product on the stage
但是，如你所见，一个签名的都没有
But, as you can see, we didn't even come close
很抱歉
well I'm really sorry, but
恐怕我不能让你继续
i'm afraid i can't allow you to xxx
如果我允许你讲述你的产品，可能对其他团队就不公平了
it would't be fair to other team if i allow you to talk about your product
我们可以让下一组继续吗
so could we have the next team on stage please
你刚才说我不能谈论产品
but you said you're not allow us to talk product on stage
但是我还是能讲5分钟的吧
but i still have the 5 mins right？
行，那你还有四分三十秒
ok you have 4：30
我在美国有一些朋友
I have some friends in The United states
他们在硅谷工作
They work in the silicon valley
他们告诉我，每当一个企业家在那里创业... ..。
They told me that whenever an entrepreneur starts a startup there...
他们被问到的第一个问题是“什么? ”
The very first question they are being asked is "What?"
产品是什么？
What is the product?
而在印度，被问“什么”的可能性要小得多
And here in India "what" is far less likely, everyone asks "why?"
为什么要创业？
Why entrepreneurship?
今天我们面临着同样的挑战。
Today we are facing a similar challenge..
就好像没人愿意听我们的”什么? ”
Like nobody is willing to listen to our "what?"
那么让我来谈谈“为什么? ”
So let me talk about The "why?"
为什么要创业？
Why entrepreneurship?
我不知道
I don't know
也许是因为在公司工作的时候，老板的"祝福"让我感到沮丧
Maybe I was frustrated at my well wisher boss in a corporate job
或许我是受到了《华尔街之狼》和《社交网络》的启发
Or maybe I was inspired by "The Wolf Of wall street" and "The social network"
又或者也许我喜欢解决现实生活中的问题
Or maybe I enjoyed solving the real life problems
你们还记得吗，在90年代，我们常常在薯片包装袋里得到免费的tazos（类似小浣熊卡）？
Do you guys remember, in 90s when we used to get those free tazos inside a chips packet?
tazos是由塑料制成的，就像闪闪发光的圆盘，上面印着卡通图案
Circular tazos made up of plastic, like shining discs which had cartoons imprinted on them
我曾经喜欢的要命
I used to be like crazy about them
我想要无穷无尽的tazos
You know all I wanted was 100s and 100s of tazos
这样我就可以把它们储存在一个空的果酱瓶子里
So that I could store them in an empty bottle of fruit jam
但是我的零用钱每周只能买得起一包
But I could only afford 1 packet of chips a week from my pocket money
当我的朋友们已经有二三十个的时候，我只有5个
While my friends were piling on to 25-30 tazos, I could manage only 5
你们现在一定在想，这又有什么难的
You guys must be thinking right now that how trivial this problem is
但在那个时候，对于一个10岁的孩子来说，这真的很难很难
But at that time for a 10 years old kid, it was a huge life problem
而且这个问题亟待解决
And it needed to be solved
然后我有了个主意
and then I got an idea
有一天，我用一枚硬币把我所有的tazos都刮花了，直到它们变得完全是白色的
One day I scratched all of my tazos with a coin until they became completely white
第二天当我去上学的时候
The next day when I went to school
就有人说纳文有一些独特的空白tazos
A news had been spread that Naveen has some unique tazos, blank tazos
你可以在上面画任何你喜欢的卡通人物
On which you can draw any of your favourite cartoon character
突然间所有人都想要我的空白tazos
and suddenly everybody wanted it
同学们准备用他们的10个、15个甚至20个tazos去换一个我的空白tazos
People were ready to trade their 10,15 and even 20 tazos just to get that one special tazo
一个月后，我又去了那家商店
One month after that, I went to the shop again
但不是去买薯片
But not to buy a packet of chips
相反，我买了一瓶新的果酱
Instead I bought a new bottle of fruit jam
这是我人生中第一个商业模式
That was my life's first business model
在那之后，我进行了很多商业冒险
I executed a lot of business ventures after that
我曾经用电脑写CD，然后在学校里卖
I used to write CDs from my computer and sold them in school
在当地赞助商的帮助下，我在大学里设法出版了我的杂志
With the help of local sponsors I managed to print my magazine in college
但是现在和过去有很大的不同
But there's a huge difference between then and now
今天我很害怕
Today I'm scared
因为竞争非常残酷
Because the competition is very ruthless
你知道今天站在这里，我不觉得自己是一个企业家
You know standing here today, I don't feel like an entrepreneur
我觉得自己好像是一个真人秀的参赛者
I feel as if I'm a contestant in a reality show
我甚至在表演前就被淘汰了
and I'm being eliminated even before performing
实际上今天的评委,我曾经的老板拉杰先生用一句话
Actually today's judge my ex boss Mr Rajat khanna had summed up the competition..
总结了什么是竞争
in a very simple sentence
他说现在每个办公室的小隔间里都坐着一位创业者
He says that there's a startup founder sitting in every office cubicle these days
那么，在成千上万的企业家中，我的位置哪里呢？
Then where am I standing among those thousands of entrepreneurs?
现在我很怀疑我自己的能力
Now I'm dubious about my own capabilities you see
然后我想，我和这些成功的企业家有什么不同？
Then I thought that how am I different with all these successful entrepreneurs?
是什么特质让他们如此特别，而我却没有呢？
What makes them special that I don't have yet?
我有我的学历，我的智慧
I have my education, my wits
我有一支坚定支持我的团队
I have a team that stands resolutely behind me
所以，从技术上讲，我也应该是成功的，对吗？
So, technically I should be successful as well, right?
但也不一定
Well not necessarily
这些成功人士还有一个共同点
You know those guys had one more extra thing in common
这也许是最重要的一点
Which was perhaps the most crucial thing
他们拒绝放弃
They refused to give up
阅读任何企业家的自传
Read any entrepreneur's biography
里面充满了鸡汤
Its filled with phrases
就像在黑暗中与困难作斗争，探索未知领域
Like a shot in the dark fighting against the odds exploring uncharted territories
那么为什么在这么早的阶段就害怕失败呢？
Then why am I scared to fail at such an early stage?
没有人第一次就成功发明发动机
Nobody invented an engine their first time
没有人第一次就成功发现新大陆
Nobody discovered an Island their first time
但是他们不断尝试，不断去做
But they kept on trying, they kept on working
如果房间是黑暗的，你必须要开灯
If the room is dark and you have to light a bulb
如果你不断摸索总机上的开关
and if you kept fumbling the switches on the switchboard
总会有一个开关能点亮该死的灯泡
Then one of the switch will light the fucking bulb
甘地曾说过。
Gandhiji has said..
不管生活中出现什么问题，只有一个解决办法。
that whatever problem may come in life, there's only one solution..
干就完事了
Bow down and get to work
所有这些导师，天使投资人和活动
all these mentors, angel investors and events
我没有所有这些外部因素
I don't have all these external factors in my hands
我的手中就只有我的工作
All I have in my hands is my work
无论何时，只要有机会。
And whenever I'll get an opportunity..
我他妈的一定会成功的
I'll fucking ace it with my work
今天一个这样的机会就从我这里被夺走了
One such opportunity was being snatched from me today
我没有放弃
i didn't give up and run back
而是选择站在这里
but i choose to stand here to face you guys
因为我要抓住每一个机会
because ultra do not loose opportunities
拉杰，你告诉我，我不能在台上卖我的产品
Rajat you told me that I cannot sell my product here on stage
所以我卖自己
Therefore I sold myself
谢谢大家
thanks guys
你刚才真的没有必要装英雄
There was no need to become a hero there
每个人都喜欢拉杰
Everyone likes Rajat
你在舞台上狠狠地打他脸
And you bashed him on the stage
你知道你带来了多少负面宣传吗？
Do you know how much negative publicity you have generated?
至少是个宣传，反正也没人在乎我们
Atleast its a publicity No one was giving a shit about us anyway
事实上，宣传给我们带来了4张名片
Infact that publicity got us 4 visiting cards
所有的名片上都写着“打电话给我的秘书”
All the cards are the ones with "call my secretary" written on them
至少一个月之内我们都不会见面
We're not gonna get a meeting atleast before a month
至少比没有名片要好
Atleast its better than zero visiting cards
我谷歌了一下。
and I googled it..
甘地从来没说过“干就完事了”
Gandhiji never said "Bow down and get to work"
是啊，我不小心说错了
Yeah I mistakenly uttered that in a flow
真的吗，纳文? ，顺其自然？
Really Naveen? in a flow?
混蛋，这是你让别人给你口的时候才说的话吧
Fucker this is what you say when you're asking for a blowjob
不是的，如果你在一句引语前加上一个著名的人物，会产生双重影响
No man, It creates a double impact if you add a famous personality in front of a quote
你为什么笑得这么开心？
Why are you smiling so much?
你爸爸离开你家的时候很愤怒，你不担心吗？
Your Dad left your home outraged, Aren't you worried about it?
一点也不担心，我会去看他的
Not a tad worried, I'll see about that
你刚刚做爱了，对吧？
You just got laid, right?
想什么呢？尤吉，现在才晚上8点
What are you looking at Yogi? Its just 8 in the evening
纳文·巴萨尔
是我
你的演讲太棒了
你都上微博热搜了
social media is crazy about your video
每个创始人和风险投资家都在谈论你
Every founder and VC is talking about you
事实上，财政部长刚刚发了一条关于你的推特
Infact the finance minister just wrote a tweet about you
真的吗？
what？ really？
开个玩笑，没那么夸张
Just kidding, It wasn't that big a deal
但是，是的，有一篇文章专门报到你的故事
But yeah YourStory wrote an article about you a while ago
顺便说一嘴，我是普尼特，这是我的名片
by the way i'm Puneet i work for a vc firm, and this is my card
我在NASCOM上看到了你的想法
I saw your idea at NASCOM conclave
非常有趣
quiet interesting
你们有空来我办公室聊一聊吗
why don't you guys drop by my office sometimes
当然，求之不得
sure we love to
那你们给我秘书打电话吧
so call my secretary
我刚想起来
infact you know what, i
我星期四下午有空，你们星期四有时间吗？
I'm free on thursday afternoon, what are you guys doing on thursday?